Okay, so today's דף Daf is דף לד. Daf Lamed Daled. We
pick up 20 lines down, asterisk is in the middle of a
line where it says עודם בירדן. Odam ba-Yarden. This is a continuation
of the ברייתא Baraita and the תוספתא. Tosefta. And
we are in the middle of the discussion of how what it
looked like when they crossed through the ירדן, Yarden, and then into
the land of כנען Kanaan and erected the stones and built the
מזבח Mizbe'ach and did the ברכות Brachos and the קללות Klalos on
הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל. Har Eival. And this is
all because the משנה Mishnah says that one of the things that
can be said, it's discussing what can be said in any language
and what can only be said in Hebrew, and the ברכות Brachos
and the קללות Klalos were something that could only be said in
לשון הקודש Lashon HaKodesh in Hebrew, and it went for a really
detailed description of that of what happened. So now we pick up.
עודם בירדן, Odam ba-Yarden, when the כהנים Kohanim were still in the
ירדן, Yarden, אמר להם יהושע, amar lahem Yehoshua, so יהושע Yehoshua and
not only the כהנים, Kohanim, all of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, יהושע
Yehoshua said to them, דעו על מה אתם עוברים את הירדן. de'u
al mah atem overim et ha-Yarden. Understand for what purpose you are
crossing the Jordan, על מנת שתורישו את יושבי הארץ מפניכם. al menat
she-torishu et yoshvei ha-aretz mi-pneichem. You have to understand that you are
going in with the condition that you are committing yourselves to driving
out the inhabitants of the land. Very harsh to our modern ears.
שנאמר, she-ne'emar, there's a פסוק pasuk in במדבר Bamidbar says, והורשתם את
כל יושבי הארץ מפניכם, ve-horashtem et kol yoshvei ha-aretz mi-pneichem, and you
shall drive out all of the inhabitants of the land, destroy them,
drive them out. אם אתם עושים כן מוטב. im atem osim ken
mutav. If you do that, great, then that's why you are entering
in in order to take possession of the land. ואם לאו, ve-im
lav, and if you don't act this way, באו מים ושטפו אתכם.
ba'u mayim u-shotefim etchem. Then the water will come and drown you.
Does it mean that if you don't agree to this right now,
that the water will drown you, or does it mean that if
you don't eventually do this, then you will suffer some overflow of
the Jordan? Not exactly clear, sounds a little bit more like the
latter. Okay. ואם לאו באו מים ושטפו אתכם. ve-im lav ba'u mayim
u-shotefim etchem. אמר
מאי אותיכם, amar mai otichem, so what does it mean אותיכם, otichem,
it will destroy אותיכם? otichem? אותי ואתכם. oti ve-etchem.
Me together with you. The waters will come and destroy us, either
if you don't agree to this condition, that is what will happen,
or if you don't ultimately do this. Okay. עודם בירדן אמר להם
יהושע. Odam ba-Yarden amar lahem Yehoshua.
So now again, they're still in the ירדן Yarden and יהושע Yehoshua
says to them, הרימו לכם איש אבן אחת על שכמו למספר שבטי
ישראל. harimu lachem ish even achat al shichmo le-mispar shivtei Yisrael. Each
person should take up a stone, based on the 12 tribes, so
each one a tribe per stone, one stone per tribe, and then
they took them from the ירדן Yarden and they erected them after
they crossed over. וכתיב ve-chtiv and the verse says, למען תהיה זאת
אות בקרבכם, le-ma'an tihyeh zot ot be-kirbechem, and this shall be a
sign in your midst, כי ישאלון בניכם מחר לאמר מה האבנים האלה
לכם, ki yish'alum bneichem machar lemor mah ha-avanim ha-eleh lachem, when your
children ask you "what are these stones?", sounds very much like a
פסוק pasuk in דברים Devarim about the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and
about the something that we recite in the סדר. Seder. Anyway, סימן
לבנים שעברו אבות הירדן. siman le-vanim she-avru avot ha-Yarden. So this is
a remembrance, this is a sign that you should remember this miracle
that for future generations that the forefathers crossed the Jordan. עודם בירדן
אמר להם יהושע. Odam ba-Yarden amar lahem Yehoshua. Again, while they were
still in the Jordan, יהושע Yehoshua said to them, while they are
on the dry land and the water is being held back. שאו
לכם מזה מתוך הירדן ממצב רגלי הכהנים הכין שתים עשרה אבנים והעברתם
אותם עמכם והנחתם אותם במלון אשר תלינו בו הלילה. se'u lachem mizeh
mi-toch ha-Yarden mi-matzav raglei ha-kohanim hachin shteim-esreih avanim ve-avartem otam imachem ve-hinachtem
otam ba-malon asher talinu vo ha-laila. Okay,
so now this is the exact פסוק pasuk about what we described
before. He says, take from the Jordan from where the כהנים Kohanim
are standing 12 stones and place it in the place where we
will sleep this night. Now, יכול בכל מלון ומלון, yachol be-chol malon
u-malon, so maybe it means every place where we're going to we
should carry these stones with us and every encampment we should erect
them? תלמוד לומר אשר תלינו בו הלילה. Talmud lomar asher talinu vo
ha-laila. No, the first encampment, that's where you will erect these stones.
And again there's a little confusion about the relationship to this and
to the מזבח Mizbe'ach and the תורה Torah that was written באר
היטב. be'er heiteiv. Anyway, this is certainly a distinctive thing. אמר רבי
יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, said רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda או רבי יוסי,
o Rabbi Yose, אבא חלפתא ורבי אליעזר בן מתיא וחנניה בן חכינאי
עמדו על אותן אבנים. Abba Chalafta ve-Rabbi Eliezer ben Matya ve-Hananya ben
Chakinai amdu al otan avanim. These great Rabbis stood on these stones,
ושיעורם כל אחת ואחת שקולה כארבעים סאה. ve-shiuram kol achat ve-achat shekulah
ke-arba'im se'ah.
Each one of them weighed the weight of 40 סאה, se'ah, which
is a huge enormous weight. וגמירי U-gmiri and we have a tradition
דטעונה דמידלי איניש לכתפיה תילתא דטעוניה הוי. de-te'una de-midlei inish le-chatfeih tilsa
de-te'uneih havei. Okay, that
and we have a tradition that the weight that a person can
carry when he can lift up a weight and put it on
his shoulders is only one-third of the weight that he would be
able to carry if somebody were to load him up. So since
יהושע Yehoshua said to load yourselves up with these stones, then that
shows us that they have the ability to carry even the weight
of 120 because the stones were 40 סאה, se'ah, so they were
enormously powerful. מכאן אתה מחשב לאשכול. Mikan ata mitchashev le-eshkol.
Now from here you can figure out how big the grape cluster
was if each one with help... somebody else and with being loaded
up by somebody else could carry a hundred and twenty סאה, se'ah,
שנאמר וישאו במוט בשנים, she'ne'emar vayisu bamot bishnayim, it says that they
carried it with a pole with two. ממה שנאמר במוט איני יודע,
mimah shene'emar bamot eini yode'a, if it says a pole obviously you
need two people, one at each end. מה תלמוד לומר בשנים? mah
talmud lomar bishnayim? What does it mean two? בשני מוטות. bishnei motot.
There were two poles. Okay, so and maybe you know there was
something, a string running between them and it was supported by two
poles. אמר רבי יצחק טורטני וטורטני דטורטני. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak turtani veturtani
deturtani.
It is poles and like poles of poles. So what this is
saying is not just that there were two poles but actually that
there were four poles. Either this word טורטני turtani means a pole
or it means a weight. But anyway the way רש״י Rashi explains
it is that you had two poles in parallel and two forming
an X and crisscrossing, and the two forming the X were below
the two in the parallel so they were giving it additional support
and therefore and by those eight people carried it and through them,
you know, four poles, eight people, and imagine how much it weighed
if one person alone could carry forty סאה se'ah just by putting
it on himself and he had an ability to carry a hundred
and twenty סאה se'ah with other people helping or with other people
loading him up, imagine what it means for eight people to carry
it. Okay, מכאן אתה... so, okay,
so where are we? אמר... הכיצד שמונה נשאו אשכול אחד? So eight,
here we have mentioned four poles carried the one cluster of grapes.
אחד נשא רימון, echad nasa rimon, one carried a pomegranate, ואחד נשא
תאנה, ve'echad nasa te'enah, one carried
a
fig, ויהושע וכלב לא נשאו כלום, ve'Yehoshua ve'Kalev lo nasu klum, and
they didn't carry anything because they knew that the bringing back of
this fruit was all a part of the way of making the
people scared and it really wasn't a way of praising the land.
אי בעית אימא משום דחשיבי, ei bayit eima mishum de'chashivei, either because
they were too important to have to do any of the carrying,
אי בעית אימא שלא היו באותו עצה, ei bayit eima she'lo hayu
be'oto eitzah, as I was saying, because they were not part of
that whole plot. Now, before we go on, I draw your attention
to רש״י. Rashi.
רש״י Rashi says that if you look at רש״י Rashi where it
says... the רש״י Rashi of שאו מזה מתוך הירדן ממצב, seu mizeh
mitoch hayarden mimatzav,
take
you know from under where the כהנים kohanim are standing, so the
people lifted up stones and the כהנים kohanim stood on the stones
and then they took the stones from under where the כהנים kohanim
were and רש״י Rashi says הם שהקימו בהר עיבל ובנו מזבח וכפלו
וקפלו בגלגל. hem she'hikimu b'har eival u'vanu mizbe'ach ve'kaplum ve'kaplum b'gilgal.
They were the ones that were put up in הר עיבל Har
Eival and they built the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so it seems like that
they are connected to the תורה Torah that was being written on
the stones באר היטב, be'er heitev, and then they were taken down
and then they were re-erected, you know, put back up in גלגל.
Gilgal. So again there are three things here: there's the altar, there's
the writing the תורה Torah on stones באר היטב, be'er heitev, and
there are these twelve stones and exactly figuring out their relationship is
not at all simple. Okay, now back back to the last line
of the גמרא. Gemara. פליגי בה רבי אמי ורבי יצחק נפחא, pligi
bah Rabbi Ami ve'Rabbi Yitzchak Napcha, there's a debate between רבי אמי
Rabbi Ami and רבי יצחק נפחא. Rabbi Yitzchak Napcha. חד אמר לדיברי
רבי יהודה כחנייתן עברו. chad amar l'divrei Rabbi Yehuda ke'chaniyatan avru. Now
we're going back to this issue about how high the waters of
the ירדן Yarden piled from yesterday. If you remember,
the first position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was it was twelve
מיל mil because the camp was twelve מיל, mil, twelve approximately kilometers,
and it took them twelve, so the time it takes for the
people to move twelve kilometers, the waters rose up those, you know,
those twelve kilometers. Of course that assumes that the rate of the
water is equal to the rate of the people, which is what
רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon pushes back and he
says no, it was twenty-five times that. Okay, that's what he says,
it was three hundred מיל. mil. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: so this was the debate. חד אמר לדיברי רבי יהודה כחנייתן
עברו chad amar l'divrei Rabbi Yehuda ke'chaniyatan avru according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that they that they passed through the ירדן Yarden the
way they were encamped, which was a square of twelve by twelve
and that's why it took twelve מיל mil to pass through. לדיברי
רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון בפיסחא אחת עברו, l'divrei Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon
b'fispacha achat avru, according to רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi
Shimon no, they became a, they went into like, you know, into
more of a more of a single, not a single file, but
you know, more of a marching procession of a line and not
of a square and therefore it took them a lot longer and
that's why the waters piled a lot higher. Now that's a little
strange because we already saw their debate wasn't about, you know, this
that רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon is saying the
waters just go a lot faster than the people travel, it's not
because they're going, you know, in a line rather than in a
square, but anyway the גמרא Gemara says maybe this is also part
of his position.
So the גמרא Gemara says וחד אמר בין מר ובין מר כחנייתן
עברו, ve'chad amar bein mar u'vein mar ke'chaniyatan avru, no,
this is the simple reading of their debate, they both agree that
they went like they encamped in a twelve by twelve square. מר
סבר אדם קל, mar savar adam kal, one person says that a
person is as fast as the water, which is a little crazy
to imagine that, ומר סבר מים קלים, u'mar savar mayim kalim, no
the waters are much faster. Okay, so so that's exactly what it
sounds like the debate actually is. Now תוספות Tosafot has a whole
huge discussion because since the whole ירדן Yarden was only fifty אמות
amot wide, תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out, you know, if they
were all in the ירדן Yarden when יהושע Yehoshua gave them the
announcements that we just read. that he gave them and the conditions
and the stipulations,
תוספות Tosafot sort of says they would have had to all have
like you know as they were getting into the ירדן Yarden move
down into the you know lower down after they entered in but
then to make room for the other people because if you think
about 50 אמות Amot wide and the camp is 12 מיל Mil
which is which is 2400 אמות Amot that means that there were
like 480 units of you know of of people in
the ירדן Yarden of a 12 מיל Mil wide by 50 אמות
Amot you know people then you had to get 480 of those
to get the whole camp so that's a lot of moving down
the ירדן Yarden and moving on the other side and תוספות Tosafot
tries to figure out if the ירדן Yarden was even long enough
to make that happen anyway so he does the math. Now the
גמרא Gemara continues: שלח לך אנשים Shlach Lecha Anashim since we're talking
about יהושע Yehoshua and crossing over and you know and entering in
and we mentioned
יהושע Yehoshua and כלב Kalev and bringing back from the land obviously
there's a lot of parallels here between what they did when they
entered the land and the sending of the spies so now we're
going to look at the sending of the spies and we're going
to try to figure out do some you know working together of
the version of it when what happens in שלח Shlach and then
when it's told over in דברים. Devarim.
שלח לך אנשים Shlach Lecha Anashim send you people. אמר ריש לקיש
Amar Reish Lakish שלח לך מדעתך shlach lecha mada'atcha okay go and
do it you know
you know you do it if you want to this is to
reconcile it where in דברים Devarim you know it says the people
you came to me you the people came to me so here
it sounds like in שלח Shlach it sounds like God is telling
him so the way you combine them the people came and then
God said you do it if you want to do it. וכי
אדם זה בורר חלק רע לעצמו Vichi adam zeh borer chelek ra
le'atzmo you know would somebody actually make you know would God have
commanded this if it was going something that was going to end
the way it did? So obviously this was only giving them allowance
to do it you know if the people wanted to do it
but it was not coming from God that's the way רש"י Rashi
reads that line.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues: והיינו דכתיב Vehaino dechativ and
this is what is meant by the verse וייטב בעיני הדבר Vayitav
be'einai hadavar
it was good in my eyes. אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish
בעיני ולא בעיניו של מקום be'einai velo be'einov shel makom I thought
it was good God gave me the allowance to do it but
God himself would not have made this choice obviously look at how
it ended. Okay. ויחפרו לנו את הארץ Veyachperu lanu et ha'aretz let
them search out for us the land. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba מרגלים לא נתכוונו אלא לבושתה של ארץ
ישראל meraglim lo nitkavnu ela lebosha shel eretz Yisrael they were trying
to you know they were trying to shame Israel they were very
intent to finding the bad stuff making it like the whole issue
from the very beginning. כתיב הכא Ketiv hacha ויחפרו לנו את הארץ
veyachperu lanu et ha'aretz let them search out the land וכתיב התם
uchetiv hatam וחפרה הלבנה ובושה החמה vechafra halevana uvosha hachamah that the
the the moon will be shamed and the and the and the
sun will be embarrassed so it's a word ויחפור veyachpor can mean
to be like ashamed so they were trying to embarrass the the
land. Okay. ואלו שמותם Ve'elu shemotam these are their names למטה ראובן
שמוע בן זכור. lemateh Reuven Shamua ben Zakur. אמר רבי יצחק Amar
Rabbi Yitzchak דבר זה מסורת בידינו מאבותינו davar zeh masoret beyadeinu me'avoteinu
we have a tradition from our forefather from you know going back
generations מרגלים על שם מעשיהם נקראו meraglim al shem ma'aseihem nikre'u
the spies you know the names they were given in the תורה
Torah meaning they were appropriately they were reflecting their actions about what
they the bad thing that they did about reporting on the land
presumably does that mean that their parent it worked out that the
parents gave them names and that's how it played out? Does it
mean that the תורה Torah is giving them more you know nicknames
based on this? Not exactly clear but anyway their names reflect eventually
what happened. Okay. ואנו לא עלה בידינו אלא אחד Ve'anu lo ala
beyadeinu ela echad and we know that this is true about all
12 of them but we only were able to figure out how
this works for one of them סתור בן מיכאל Satur ben Michael
סתור Satur the son of מיכאל Michael סתור שסתר מעשיו של הקדוש
ברוך הוא Satur shesatar ma'asav shel hakadosh baruch hu סתור Satur means
to destroy destroyed the acts of God meaning God's desire to bring
them in you know to the you know to the land and
מיכאל
שעשה עצמו מך UMichael she'asah atzmo mach he made himself and this
is like a euphemism he made like א-ל El מיכאל Michael he
made it like God was weak that said that God would not
have the power to bring them into the land. אמר רבי יוחנן
Amar Rabbi Yochanan אף אנו נאמר af anu nomar let's see if
we can figure out some of the others this is an interesting
game. Okay so we can also say אף אנו נאמר af anu
nomar נחבי בן ופסי. Nachbi ben Vafsi. Okay how
how can we interpret that? מעין נחבי שהחבי דבריו של הקדוש ברוך
הוא Ma'ein Nachbi shehechbi devarav shel hakadosh baruch hu נחבי Nachbi means
he like hid God's words meaning that he he did not report
things as they was you know he hid the truth and the
the and what certainly what God would be able to do to
help them with the land. וופסי uVafsi what does וופסי uVafsi mean?
שפיסע על מידותיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא shepisa al midotav shel hakadosh
baruch hu he like skipped over you know God's attributes like you
know ignored God's attributes and did not give it them recognize the
power that God would have.
Okay. ויעלו בנגב ויבא עד חברון Vaya'alu banegv vayavo ad Chevron they
went up in the south and they came to Hebron. ויבא מבעי
ליה Vayavo mibei lei it says ויעלו בנגב vaya'alu banegv so it
should say ויבאו עד חברון vayavo'u ad Chevron why
is ויבא vayavo singular? אמר רבא Amar Rava מלמד שפירש כלב מעצת
מרגלים melamed sheperash Kalev me'atzat meraglim
כלב Kalev separated out from the sort of the scheme you know
the plan of the מרגלים meraglim and so not only did it
mean he held himself and he did not agree to go along.
wrong, but he physically broke off from the group and went on
a little, you know, adventure of his own. והלך ונשתטח על קברי
אבות Vahalach venishtatach al kivrei avos
and he went and he prostrated himself on the graves of the
fathers of the forefathers Abraham Isaac and Jacob who are in Hevron
and the Imahos. And אמר להן אבותי בקשו עלי רחמים. Amar lahen
avosai bikshu alai rachamim. My,
you know, fathers pray, ask for compassion for me. שנצל מעצת מרגלים
Shenatzeil me'atzat meraglim that I should be saved from the plot, you
know, it's very hard to stand up against that pressure. And that's
why the Torah says ועבדי כלב עקב היתה רוח אחרת עמו. V'avdi
Calev eikev hayta ruach acheret imo. You know, he had that courage,
he was able to withstand it. So he went to Hevron and
he prayed. And of course, you know, why are we identifying Calev?
A, because of the רוח אחרת ruach acheret and the Torah sort
of singles that out, but also eventually, you know, Calev got Hevron
when they went into the land. And if you look at Rashi,
actually we're going to get to it in a minute. Okay. יהושע
כבר ביקש משה עליו רחמים. Yehoshua kvar bikeish Moshe alav rachamim. Yehoshua
didn't have to pray because Moshe had already prayed on his behalf,
שנאמר ויקרא משה להושע בן נון יהושע. Shene'emar Vayikra Moshe l'Hoshea bin
Nun Yehoshua. So what does Yehoshua mean? יה יושיעך מעצת מרגלים. Yah
yoshia'acha me'atzat meraglim. God should save you from the from the plan
of the scheme of the Meraglim. והיינו דכתיב V'hainu dechtiv and because
Calev went to Hevron to pray, that fits out and says ועבדי
כלב עקב היתה רוח אחרת עמו. V'avdi Calev eikev hayta ruach acheret
imo. It's because he had a different spirit, so what's, what's the
point? והיינו דכתיב. V'hainu dechtiv. So it says ואביאתיו V'aviosiv and I
will bring him, and that's what Rashi points out, אל הארץ אשר
בא שמה, El ha'aretz asher ba shama, the land he went to.
So what does it mean? It's very particular. Not the whole land
of Canaan, specifically Hevron and we know that in the end Calev
got Hevron. By the way, very interesting if you look at Tosfos,
אבותי בקשו עלי רחמים. Avosai bikshu alai rachamim. Tosfos says ואם תאמר
והאמר פרק מי שמתו דמתי לא ידעי מידי מידי V'im tomar v'ha'amar
perek Mi shemeto demesei lo yad'ei midei midei that the dead don't
know anything. So you know, once they're dead they're dead, so how
can you pray? It's not like they have their spirits and you
can talk to them and you can pray to them. Of course
we know that often people do. So ומשמע מסקנא ואפילו אבות העולם
U'mashma maskana v'afilu avos ha'olam even the great Abraham Isaac and Jacob
don't know what's going on in this world. ויש לומר דעל ידי
תפילה שזה מתפלל מודיעים להם שכך נתפלל. V'yesh lomar d'al yedei tefillah
shezeh mitpallel modiyim lahem shekach nitpallel. If you pray, then up in
heaven they'll they'll inform them down there on the earth somebody is
praying to you for the wants your help XYZ. You know, you
to help in, you know, pray to God. Okay. ואחי אמר בפרק
שני דתניא למה יוצאין לבית קברות כדי שיבקשו עליהם מתים רחמים. V'hachi
amar beperek sheni detanya lama yotzin l'veis kvaros k'dei sheyivakshu aleihem meisim
rachamim. And there's this idea that the dead will, you know, pray
on our behalf. It's a very sensitive issue because some rationalist rabbis
were very against it because it winds up our people really, you
know, praying praying to asking for their help to pray or are
they praying to the dead? You know, and the whole idea of
an intermediary between yourself and God and so on. But anyway, clearly,
you know, we see that there is some element of this, and
it both has to be dealt with theologically, like about what does
it mean to what's the proper way in which one solicits the
aid of the dead and, you know, and also the question about
metaphysically, like you know, do they really know
and are aware of what's happening? Okay. Now we continue in the
Gemara.
ושם אחימן ששי ותלמי. Vesham Achiman Sheshai veTalmai. There was Achiman Sheshai
and Talmai, the children of the giant. אחימן, Achiman, so what does
it mean? מיומן שבאחיו. Meyuman sheba'achiv.
He was like the right-hand man, he was the strongest. ששי שמשים
את הארץ כשחיתות Sheshai shemesim es ha'aretz keshichitus that he made the
land like, you know, like Rashi says like deep impressions, he was
so heavy, he made like these deep craters in the land. תלמי
שמשים את הארץ תלמים תלמים Talmai shemesim es ha'aretz telamim telamim also
made the lands
like furrows because their steps were so deep, you know, they made
these like craters. דבר אחר Davar acher אחימן בנה ענת Achiman bana
Anat
this is not really a דבר אחר, davar acher, it's not it's
not explaining the name of the meaning of their of their names,
but it's telling you a point. Achiman built the city Anat, ששי
בנה אלאש, Sheshai bana Alash, תלמי בנה תלבוש. Talmai bana Talbush. Okay.
ילדי הענק, Yelidei Ha'anak, what does it mean children of the Anak?
שמעניקין חמה בקומתם Shema'anikin chama bekomasam that they are like, you know,
that they like the word ענק Anak can mean like a neck.
So Rashi says it's like their neck pierces through the heaven, you
know, and they sort of and or they it looks like it's
piercing through the sun, they're so high. Okay. וחברון שבע שנים נבנתה.
VeHevron sheva shanim nivnesa. She Hevron was built seven years before Tzoan
of Egypt. מאי נבנתה? Mai nivnesa? What does it mean built? אילימא
נבנתה ממש? Eilima nivnesa mamash? It was built seven years. אפשר אדם
בונה בית לבנו קטן? Efshar adam boneh bayis l'vno katan? So Canaan
was the youngest son, is it possible קודם לבנו גדול? kodem l'vno
gadol? דכתיב בני חם כוש ומצרים ופוט וכנען? Dechtiv bnei Cham Kush
u'Mitzrayim u'Put v'Chanaan? That
that the sons children of Cham, you know, Mitzrayim comes well before
Canaan. So why would Cham have built a son for Canaan, a
city for Canaan because Hevron is in the land of Canaan before
he built a city for his older son
Mitzrayim, the city of Tzoan? אלא, Ela, so what does it mean
it was built seven years before? שהייתה מבונה אחד משבעה בצוען. Shehayta
mevunah echad mishiva beTzoan. It was seven times more built up. Now
presumably not the city but the land itself was seven times better
than the land of Tzoan. Now this is of course a little
bit ironic because ואין לך V'ein lacha ואין לך טרשין בכל ארץ
ישראל יותר מחברון. V’ein lecha tarsha be’chol Eretz Yisrael yoter mi’Chevron. You
have no place in history of that’s more like rocky, unfertile, you
know, than חברון, Chevron, דקברי בה שיכבי, De’kivrei bei shichvei, and
that’s why the dead are buried there because it’s not good land
for anything else. ואין לך מעולה בכל הארצות יותר מארץ מצרים, V’ein
lecha me’ulah be’chol ha’aratzos yoter mi’Eretz Mitzrayim, and there is no land
that is more fertile than the land of Egypt. שנאמר כגן ה'
כארץ מצרים, Shene’emar k’gan Hashem k’Eretz Mitzrayim,
like the garden of God. ואין לך מעולה בכל ארץ מצרים יותר
מצען, V’ein lecha me’ulah be’chol Eretz Mitzrayim yoter mi’Zoan, and there’s no
better fertile place in all of Egypt than צען, Zoan, דכתיב כי
היו בצען שריו, De’chsiv ki hayu be’Zoan sarav, that the officers that
were sent like the dignitaries, you know, for, from Israel
from the land of Israel to מצרים, Mitzrayim, they dwelt in צען.
Zoan. That’s obviously was a very important city, presumably it’s one of
the best cities or the best. So ואפילו הכי, v’afilu hachi, so
even though חברון Chevron is like the the most rocky and צען
Zoan is the most fertile, חברון מבונה אחת משבעה בצען. Chevron mevuna
achat mi’shiva be’Zoan. It’s seven times more built up. I don’t know
what built up means. So you know רש"י Rashi says מיושבת בפירות.
meyusheves b’peiros.
So what is it saying? How could this land be rocky and
that land be fertile and this be more built up by fruits?
It’s probably more easy to understand this as a spiritual statement rather
than as the physical quality of the land. Okay. So then it
says like this.
וחברון טרשים הואי, Ve’Chevron tarshin havai, was חברון Chevron really like this
rocky place? והכתיב ויהי מקץ ארבעים שנה ויאמר אבשלום אל המלך אלכה
נא, Vehachsiv vayehi miketz arba’im shanah vayomer Avshalom el hamelech elcha na,
let me go, you know, back to חברון. Chevron. ואמר רבי אביו
ואיתימא רבה בר בר חנה, V’amar Rabbi Avyu v’isima Rabbah bar bar
Chana, חנן שהלך להביא כבשים מחברון. Chanan shehalach l’havi kevasim mi’Chevron.
He went to חברון Chevron to bring sheep that he you know
for he says I want to go bring a sacrifice. ותניא אילי
ממואב, Vesanya eili mi’Moav, if you want the good rams you get
them from מואב, Moav,
וכבשים מחברון. ve’kevasim mi’Chevron. And the if you want sheep, you know,
good then lambs, you get them from חברון. Chevron. So presumably if
it’s a rocky place that’s not where you have lambs? No. The
גמרא Gemara says מינה, Minah, oh that’s exactly the point. איידי דקלישא
ארעא עבדא רעיא, Aidi deklisha ara avda ra'aya, okay, ושמין קניינא, v’shamin
kinyana, because the land is weak and doesn’t have a lot of
it’s not so fertile, that’s good grazing land. That’s when you have
all of that like you know grass and you know other vegetation
and you’re not growing other things and that makes you have you
know good fatty flocks. So okay, go figure that one out and
we will pick up with this tomorrow.